（２人）あっ。
（百合亜）おかえりなさい。
Welcome back.
Thank you.
（森雪）ただいま。
（南部）あぁ…。　ふふっ。
（古代進）ふっ。
Welcome back
ふふっ。
Planet Iscandar... An Earth-type planet whose surface is eighty percent water.
（太田）イスカンダル星
表面の約８０％が　海に覆われた→
地球型の惑星です。
We made it.
（島）ここまで
来たんだな　俺たち。
ああ。
Yeah.
Crew of the Yamato. This is Okita, your captain.
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]（沖田十三）
ヤマトの諸君。　艦長　沖田だ。→
我々は
ついに　イスカンダルへ来た。→
We have finally reached Iscandar.
Look... Iscandar lies before you.
見たまえ。　今　諸君の目の前に
イスカンダルがある。→
As your captain, I have just one thing I'd like to say to you.
この機会に艦長として　ひと言だけ
諸君に　申し上げたい。
Thank you... That is all.
ありがとう。　以上だ。
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]　本艦は　これより→
Iscandar will now guide the Yamato to the planet's surface.
イスカンダルからの誘導に従って
着陸します。→
Surface temperature is 27 degrees. Air pressure is 1,023 hectopascals.
地表は　気温２７度。→
気圧１０２３ヘクトパスカル。→
風力２　南の風。→
On the Beaufort scale, the wind is 2, to south. The sea is calm, and the sky is clear.
海上は　うねりもなく
穏やかな晴天です。
We will return Yurisha. Kodai and Niimi, come with me.
（真田）これから
ユリーシャを送り届ける。→
古代と新見君は
私と一緒に来たまえ。
Yes, sir.
（古代・新見）はい。
（真田）ん？　ふっ。
You, too, Mori.
森君もだ。
Yes, sir.
はい。
The city is very quiet.
静かな街だな。
She will be here soon.
（イスカンドロイド）
間モナク　オ見エニナリマス。
Welcome home, Yurisha.
（スターシャ　イスカンダル語で）
And you, as well, Sasha.
No, this is Mori Yuki...
（ユリーシャ　イスカンダル語で）
She is an Earthling
あの…。
（真田）どうやら　森君を→
Uh...
It seems she thought Mori was Sasha.
サーシャだと思ったらしい。
（２人）えっ？
She lost her life on Mars, bringing us the Wave Motion Core.
あの方は　波動コアを運ぶ途中→
火星で　命を落とされました。
はっ…　サーシャ。
Sasha...
The Earth owes her its survival.
地球の恩人です。
そうでしたか。
I see...
And yet, you used the Wave Motion Energy as a weapon.
なのに　あなた方は→
波動エネルギーを
兵器に転用してしまった。
（２人）んん…。
But that was...
ですが　それは…。
（真田）古代！
Kodai!
あっ。→
What is your name?
あなた　お名前は？
古代進です。
Susumu Kodai.
I am Executive Officer Shiro Sanada, here on the Captain's behalf. She is...
（真田）
私は　艦長代行として来ました→
副長の真田志郎。　彼女は…。
（新見）情報長の新見薫です。
Information Officer Kaoru Niimi.
Yurisha, tell me what you have seen.
ユリーシャ
あなたが見てきたものを→
私に伝えなさい。→
I shall speak with the people from Earth afterward.
地球の方々と話すのは
そのあとです。
Yes.
はい。
（南部）うそでしょう？
You're kidding me...
どういうことですか？
What do you mean?
Yeah, she said we can't have the Cosmo Reverse System.
（吉田）ああ。
コスモリバースシステムは　渡せないって…。
Does that mean she wants everyone on Earth to die?!
（北野）地球人なんか
滅びた方がいいってことか？
From what I heard, she simply wants some time.
（桐生）
私が聞いた話じゃ　しばらく→
時間を置くってことらしいけど。
Either way, it's an insult!
（岩田）
どっちにしても　バカにしてるぜ！
Will she really give it to us?
（沢村）
ほんとに渡してくれるのかなぁ？
We just need to believe.
（篠原）信じるっきゃないっしょ。
Everyone's uneasy...
みんな　不安になってるな。
Of course they are... Everyone was happy we'd finally made it.
しかたないだろ。　みんな→
ここまで来てという思いが
あるんだ。
Keep your feet on the ground.
（島）「浮き足だつな！」。
あっ。
Is what the Captain would say.
（島）と　艦長なら言うだろうな。
We need to do something.
なんとかしないとな。
Um, Medic Harada has a suggestion!
（真琴）
え～っと　原田衛生士　意見具申！
あはは～！
うわ～！
≪わあ～！
≪うふふっ！
Hoshina, can you swim?
（百合亜）星名　泳げるの？
（星名）たぶん。
I think so.
Nice idea, Makoto!
（西条）真琴　ナイスアイディア！
（真琴）ふふふっ。
（桐生）そうそう。
そこに海があるんだから→
Yeah, the sea is right here! We need to let off some steam.
ガス抜きは　必要です。
Exactly.
（真琴）だよね。
（桐生）加藤さんは？　来ないの？
Where's Kato? Isn't he coming?
Oh, yeah!
（西条）そうそう。
（真琴）それがね→
Well...
Tokugawa got him.
なんか
徳川さんに誘われたみたい。
Oh...
（桐生）な～んだ。
おお～！
ヒュ～！
（真琴）おお～！
（沢村）篠さん！
Shino!
（篠原）ええ～…。
（玲）次　あなたの番よ。
It's your turn.
（篠原）高い。　高すぎ…　うわっ！→
High... Too high.
うわぁ～～!!
バシャーーン！
（メルダ）ふん。
（一同）おお～！
（岩田）ブラボー！
（玲）やるわね。
Not bad.
当然だ。
Naturally.
（沢村）篠さぁ～ん。
あっ　あぁ…。
Shino...
Nature's so nice...
（土岐）自然っていいなぁ。
（榎本）まったくだ。
You've got that right.
（宮澤）男って　バカ。
Guys are so stupid.
This really is nice...
やっぱり　いいな。
ん？
Hmm?
Ships belong on the sea.
艦は　海の上がいちばんだ。
そうだな。
Yeah.
I'm not good with waiting.
待つのは苦手だ。
（島）ああ。
Yeah.
I see... So Lord Desler has passed away.
（スターシャ）
そうですか…。　デスラー総統は→
亡くなられたのですね。
（ヒス）はい。→
Yes, the Yamato saved us. We have no further issues with them.
我々は　ヤマトに救われました。→
もう　彼らに対するこだわりは
ありません。
あなた方にはなくとも
私にはあります。
Even if you do not, I do.
Abelt...
（心の声）≪アベルト…≫
（デスラー・回想）
((私の夢は　ガミラスと→
My dream is the great unification of Garmillas and Iscandar.
イスカンダルの大統合だ))
That would be impossible... Our ideals are too different.
（スターシャ）((それは無理よ。
私たちと　あなたたちとでは→
思想が違いすぎる。
私たちの使命は…))
Our task is...
（デスラー）((ならば
その使命を　私が果たそう))
Then I shall fulfill your task.
I promise you that I will grant your wish.
（デスラー）
((約束するよ。　君の願いは→
この私が　かなえてみせる。→
そして　全ての星に平和を))
And I will bring peace to all the planets.
Even if I save the humans, they'll follow the same path you did.
≪地球人を救っても
また　あなたと同じ道を…≫
And I would add that it was
（ヒス）それと　我々を救ったのは→
the cannon that uses Wave Motion Energy which saved us.
波動エネルギーを使った
大砲であったと→
申し添えておきます。
（スターシャ）あとのことは
こちらで判断します。
We can handle the rest on our own.
（ヒス　ガミラス語で）
Rud Iscandar.
はぁ…。　あっ。
（スターシャ）ユリーシャ。
どうか　地球人に→
Yurisha?
Please give the Cosmo Reverse System to the Earthlings.
コスモリバースシステムを。
I am considering it.
検討中です。
彼らは→
They are like neither the Iscandarians nor the Garmillans.
イスカンダル人とも
ガミラス人とも違います。
The Yamato used the Wave Motion Gun in self-defense.
ヤマトが　波動砲を使ったのは
その身を守るため。
生き抜くためでした。
In order to survive.
The scent of the sea... When did I last smell that?
潮の香りだ。
前に嗅いだのは　いつだったろう。
I'd like to take this odor back...
（佐渡）取り戻したいもんですなぁ
この香りを。
Yeah, that's why we're here.
ああ。　そのために来たんだ。
（ＡＵ０９）潮ノ香リナラバ
合成デ　再現可能デス。
The smell of salt air can be replicated artificially.
You're a boring little robot, you know? I'll teach you to drink sometime.
（佐渡）
ほんと　つまらんヤツじゃなぁ。
今度　酒の飲み方　教えてやる。
酒ハ飲メマセン。
機能障害ヲ　起コス確率７８％。
I cannot drink.
It has a seventy-eight percent chance of causing a system error.
You really are boring!
（佐渡）まったくもって
つまらんヤツじゃ。
（ＡＵ０９）冷エテキマシタ。
今夜ハ　熱燗デスネ。
It's gotten cold. This is a night for hot sake.
Yes. I understand that they could not have made it so far otherwise.
（スターシャ）ええ。　そうしなければ→
ここまで来られなかった
ということも分かっています。→
And that they used the power to save their enemy.
その力で　敵を救ったことも。
でも…。→
But...
Yes, the will to survive...
そうね。　生き抜こうとする意志→
彼らには　それがある。→
They have that.
I understand that.
分かっているわ…。
I must tell them about you. She was here, as well...
あなたのことは
伝えなければいけない。
彼女も来ていた。
でも　そうしたら→
But if I do, I'll never see you again...
あなたとは　もう…。→
This planet is too sad...
この星は　悲しすぎる。
わあ～　きれい。
なんていう花？
So pretty.
What are these flowers called?
（ユリーシャ）翠水晶。
Blue Crystal.
翠水晶。
Blue Crystal?
地球にも　また咲くんだろうか？
こんな花が。
Will flowers like these bloom on Earth again?
In the language of flowers, they mean "hidden life" and "hidden emotion."
（ユリーシャ）花言葉は
「秘めた生命　秘めた想い」。
秘めた生命…。
Hidden life?
When a planet bears life,
生命を宿した惑星には→
その星の物質と
生命の進化の記憶が→
its matter, and its life forms' evolutionary memories,
時空を超えた波動として
存在している。→
exist as a Wave Motion, beyond time and space.
The planet's element, matter that contains its emotions, releases those memories.
その記憶を解き放つのは→
星の想いを宿した物質
星のエレメント。
コスモリバースはね→
Without that element here, the Cosmo Reverser cannot be completed.
そのエレメントが
ここに来なくては　完成しないの。
あっ。
（ユリーシャ）地球を救うのなら→
The only way to save the Earth was for you to come here.
ここに
来てもらうよりほかになかった。
And you came.
そして　あなたたちは来た→
ヤマトと共に。
With the Yamato.
星の想いを宿した物質　それが…。
Matter that contains the planet's emotions?
That is...
（ユリーシャ）そうよ。
Yes.
いつまで待たされるんですかね？
How long do you suppose they'll keep us waiting?
というか
渡してくれるんでしょうか？
Do you think they'll even give it to us?
今は信じよう。
≪（乗員）おい　なんだ!?
For now, let us have faith.
Hey, what is that?
（星名）失礼ですが
ご用件を　お聞かせ願えますか？
Excuse me, but may I ask what you want?
（スターシャ）ご心配には及びません。
（２人）あっ。
There is no need for concern.
スターシャさん。
Starsha!
I have come to give you the Cosmo Reverser.
あなた方に　コスモリバースを→
お渡ししに来たのです。
エレメント…　ですか？
（スターシャ）ええ。
An element?
Yes.
And what is required for use as an element?
それで　エレメントとして
必要なものとは？
この艦です。
（古代・真田）あっ。
This ship.
つまり　それは…。
In... In other words...
（スターシャ）この艦を作り替えます。
I shall remake this ship.
And the Yamato itself will become the system for the Cosmo Reverser.
そして　このヤマトそのものが→
コスモリバースの
システムとなるのです。
分かりました。
Understood.
決定が正しかったことを
祈るのみです。
I must simply pray my decision was the correct one.
We made the hand of salvation you offered us into a weapon of destruction.
差し伸べていただいた
救いの手を→
我々は
破壊兵器に作り替えてしまった。
We are well aware of the gravity of this deed.
その責は　重く捉えています。
あなた方が　波動砲と呼ぶもの→
What you call the Wave Motion Gun...
あれを最初に作ったのは
私たちです。
We were the first to make it.
（３人）あっ！
Iscandar once used its power
（スターシャ）
かつてイスカンダルは　その力で→
to stain the Large Magellanic Cloud with blood, to forge a mighty empire.
大マゼランを血に染め
大帝国を作り上げていったのです。
（スターシャ）
あの兵器の恐ろしさは　私たちが→
More than any other, we know the terror of that weapon.
いちばんよく知っています。→
だから
どこにも　技術供与しなかった。
So we never gave the technology to anyone.
Promise me...
約束してください
私たちのような愚行を→
That you will never repeat our foolish act.
繰り返さないと。
お約束します。
I promise.
ん？
（スターシャ）あなた→
You... Susumu Kodai, was it?
古代進さんでしたね？
はい。
Yes...
少し　よろしいかしら？
May I have a word?
（メルダ）私たちは　これから
どこへ向かっていけばいいのだ。
Where are we going now?
ここは墓地ですか？
Is this a graveyard?
Iscandar's people sleep below.
（スターシャ）イスカンダルの人々は
この下に眠っています。→
Everyone, save the two of us, is here.
私たち二人を除いて　皆　ここに。
街を見て
気付いていたのでしょう？
I imagine you realized this once you saw the town.
（スターシャ）そんな悲しさは
この星だけで十分。
This planet is the only one that need suffer this sadness.
Eiji Ishizu
あっ…。
Mamoru Kodai
How?
なんで…。　なぜ　兄の名前が？
Why is my brother's name here?
（スターシャ）コントロールを失って
イスカンダルに墜落した→
He was on board a Garmillan prisoner-transport ship
ガミラスの捕虜護送船の中に。
あっ。
that crashed on Iscandar.
（スターシャ）
地球人の生体サンプルとして→
They were carrying him as a bio-sample of humanity.
輸送していたのでしょう。→
でも　助かったのは　彼だけだった。
But he was the only one to survive.
I managed to hide him from Garmillas. But his body was already...
ガミラスの目を盗み
なんとか保護しましたが→
そのとき　すでに　彼の体は…。→
結局　私は　誰も助けられなかった。
In the end, I couldn't save anyone...
I see.
そうでしたか。
（守）私は　国連宇宙軍所属→
I am Captain of the Cosmo Navy Destroyer Yukikaze, Mamoru Kodai.
駆逐艦ユキカゼ艦長　古代守だ。→
私は　ガミラスの捕虜となり→
I was captured by Garmillans, and was being transported as an experimental sample.
実験サンプルとして
護送される途中→
難破したところを
イスカンダルの女性に→
When the ship crashed, I was saved by an Iscandarian woman.
助けられた。　そして　地球の艦が→
And she told me that a ship from Earth was heading here.
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]　ここに向かっていることを
彼女から聞いた。→
このメッセージが
届いているということは→
If you're hearing this message, you must have made it.
君たちは　無事に
たどりついたということだろう。→
できることなら
俺も　君たちの艦で→
I wish I could return to Earth with you, aboard your ship.
一緒に　地球へ帰りたい。→
だが　それまで
俺の体は　もちそうにない。→
But it appears I will not last that long.
最期に
言い残しておきたいことは２つ。→
Before I die, there are two things I wish to say.
１つは　俺たちは異星人とだって→
The first is that we can come to an understanding with the aliens.
理解し合えるということだ。
（守）俺は
それを　この星に来て教えられた。
Since I arrived, I have learned that.
I hope you will not forget it.
それは　忘れないでほしい。
And second, I want you to tell my brother, Susumu...
そして　もう１つは
弟の進に伝えてほしい。
あっ。
進　俺の分まで生きてくれ。
Susumu, live for me, as well!
生きて　必ず→
Live, and see the Earth when it's become blue once more!
青い姿を取り戻した地球を
瞳に　焼き付けてくれ。
（守）貴艦の航海の安全を祈る。→
I pray for your safe voyage.
どうか　地球へ　無事な帰還を。
May you return safely to Earth!
そうか　古代はここで…。
I see, Kodai passed away here.
（真田）冷たい宇宙空間でなく
この星の大地で→
He sleeps peacefully. Not in the coldness of space, but here, in this land...
静かに眠ることができたのです。
（新見）うぅ…　ううっ…。
Let us return, Sanada.
帰ろう　真田君。
それが　彼の望みであり→
It was his wish and our task.
我々の使命だ。
はい。
Yes, sir.
本当なの？
（ユリーシャ）ええ。→
Is that true?
Yes, I shall go to Garmillas.
私は　ガミラスに赴きます。
There, I shall assist the people.
かの地で
人々の支えとなるために。
（ガミラス語で）
Irun Yurisha
うん。
（ユリーシャ）雪→
Yuki, this is a sign of the bond between us.
これは　私たちの絆の証し。
Hidden life... Hidden emotions.
（ユリーシャ）秘めた生命。
秘めた想い。
あっ…。
メンタリティーは同じだな。
We share a mindset.
ふふっ。　こっちのセリフだ。
That's my line.
ふふっ。　あっ。
ふっ。
本艦は
コスモリバースの受領を終え→
The Yamato will now finish reception of the Cosmo Reverser and return to Earth.
これより
地球へ向け　帰還の途に就く。
帰ろう　ふるさとへ。
Let us return home.
（真田）錨　上げぇ！
Weigh anchor!
さようなら　古代君。
Goodbye, Kodai...
Farewell, my other self.
（ユリーシャ）さよなら　もう一人の私。
（スターシャ）さようなら　守。
Farewell, Mamoru...
Episode 24: The Distant Promised Land
With Iscandar behind it, the Yamato hurries back to Earth.
Will they make it?
They arrive at the Balun gate, hoping to speed their return.
But there, they see that man... Their enemy. Can they see a future beyond him?
Next time: The Forever War.
There are 143 days left before humanity is extinct.
台風情報からお伝えします。
大型の台風１８号の影響で、
四国から東北までの広い範囲で激
しい雨が降った。
台風はこの後、紀伊半島から
東海地方に上陸するおそれもあり